Finding Aid for Robert W. Schoening papers, ca. 1919-1923
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert W. Schoening papers circa 1919-1923
Schoening, Robert W.
2013014 Aa2
German-born resident of Saginaw, Michigan; worked variously as a laborer, mechanic, shop foreman, factory superintendent, and traveling salesman. Includes scattered correspondence and unpublished literary works and essays with details of early cross-country automobile travel on the Yellowstone Trail and Lincoln Highway and perspectives on Michigan's manufacturing economy.
0.2 linear feet
16.1 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Joel Corner (Donor No. 1073 ) and Samuel S. Corner (Donor No. 10735 ) in 2012 1073
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The original manuscripts are at the Bentley Library. The entire collection has been digitized and is available as a PDF file for each document and as TIFF files for each page. Links to the digitized document are provided in the contents list.
Robert W. Schoening was born in Germany on September 13, 1878 to Charles and Lena Pettit Schoening and married Elizabeth (Lizzie) Maud Frazer in Port Huron, Michigan on June 18, 1902. He worked as a laborer, mechanic, shop foreman, factory superintendent, and a traveling salesman in his lifetime.
In 1919 he was offered a position as a salesman in the western United States; he and his wife subsequently drove from Saginaw, Michigan to Portland, Oregon along the Yellowstone Trail transcontinental automobile route and spent the ensuing year and a half traveling around the Pacific Northwest, California, Nevada, and Utah. The couple returned to Michigan in 1921 (partially by way of the Lincoln Highway) and Schoening produced several manuscripts (perhaps intended for publication in different magazines) that detailed their experiences on the road, with descriptions of places they visited (including Flint, Chicago, Reno, Salt Lake City, and Yellowstone), their daily routine in driving and camping, and the often tenuous conditions of the roads and highways.
In addition to his travelogues, Schoening was an aspiring author (at one point he sought publishing advice from author James Oliver Curwood) and wrote philosophical, economic, and practical essays as well as a novel (Red Biz) that explored conditions and relationships in an early twentieth century factory and which he sought to have published shortly before his death on June 3, 1923 in Saginaw, Michigan.
The Robert W. Schoening papers are primarily of interest due to their detailed description of his cross-country automobile trips and extensive traveling through the western United States from 1919 to 1921. Other writings reveal period attitudes towards capitalism, patriotism, and industrialism. The collection includes original manuscripts and correspondence as well as digitized images of these works created by Schoening's family. The Robert W. Schoening papers are divided into three series, Correspondence, Essays, and Writings.
Subjects:
Schoening, Robert W., b. 1878.; Automobile travel--West (U.S.); Buick automobile.; Business ethics--Fiction.
Genre Terms:
Digital files.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes letters written by Schoening to James Oliver Curwood (seeking literary advice of the author and screenwriter from Owosso, Mich.) and G. Cameron-Émslie (a request for the recipient, an editor at Physical Culture Publishing Corporation, to consider the manuscript of Red Biz). Also included is a letter from one S.G. Randall, a manager at a saw mill in Westwood, California (and personal acquaintance of Schoening and his wife), detailing his experience implementing Schoening's saw hammering methodology.
  - Cameron-Émslie, G. 1923, 1 digital files TIFF files (Box 1)
  - Curwood, James Oliver 1920, 1 digital files TIFF files (Box 1)
  - Randall, S. G. 1920, .PDF and .TIFF files (Box 1)
    (Copy; original letter is with "Scientific Saw Hammering")
- Essays
  The Essays series includes various short, nonfiction works on written by Schoening on both philosophical and practical topics. These include "The American Soul Aflame" (a treatise on America's embodiment of humanist ideals and democratic values), "The Price of Fun" (an incomplete piece that explores issues of leisure and class), and "What Is Business?" (a review of modern capitalism and social inequalities). "Scientific Saw Hammering" lays out an alternative methodology for straightening and tensioning large saw blades and reflects Schoening's experience in the lumber industry.
  - "Fun, Fun, Fun: The Price of Fun" circa 1919-1923 (Box 1)
  - "Scientific Saw Hammering," circa 1920, .PDF and .TIFF files
  - "The American Soul Aflame," circa 1919-1923, .PDF and .TIFF files (Box 1)
  - "What Is Business?" undated, .PDF and .TIFF files (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  The Manuscripts series contain longer pieces, both fiction and nonfiction, that reflect Schoening's interest in automobiles, travel, and socio-economic perspectives on the United States and Michigan. Both "The Automobile" and "The Story of Our 'Billy' Buick" provide accounts (with slight variations) of Schoening's experiences as a travelling salesman in the western United States from 1919 to 1921 and the cross-country journeys he took with his wife as he set forth and returned from this endeavor. These pieces include firsthand accounts of life on the road and the often harrowing conditions of highways in the early twentieth century, with narrations of stops in Flint, Chicago, Portland, Salt Lake City, Yellowstone, and other locales. The manuscript Red Biz is also significant for its depiction of conditions in a factory and the relations between the titular floor manager and his employees immediately after the first World War, with additional domestic scenes and back story set in late nineteenth-century Ann Arbor and Saginaw.
  - "The Automobile"
    - Handwritten Copy circa 1921, .PDF and .TIFF files (Box 1)
    - Typescript 1921 (Box 1)
  - "The Story of Our 'Billy' Buick" circa 1921, .PDF and .TIFF files (Box 1)
  - Red Biz, circa 1923, .PDF and .TIFF files (Box 1)